<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>nonfiction studios inc. blog</title>
    <link>http://nonfiction.ca/blog</link>
    <language>en</language>
    <webMaster>darron@nonfiction.ca (Darron Froese)</webMaster>
    <pubDate>2011-06-17T11:09:20-06:00</pubDate>
    <copyright>Copyright 2011</copyright>
    <ttl>60</ttl>
    <description>a blog by nonfiction studios inc.</description>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working to earn your trust.</title>
      <link>http://nonfiction.ca/blog/2011/06/17/working-to-earn-your-trust-post.html</link>
      <pubDate>2011-06-17 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://nonfiction.ca/blog/2011/06/17/working-to-earn-your-trust-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Was thinking about how I interact with car mechanics lately - since I&amp;#8217;m due for another oil change. &lt;em&gt;Most&lt;/em&gt; of the time, I decline their offers for additional services reflexively. This isn&amp;#8217;t because I know that my vehicle doesn&amp;#8217;t need the service - it&amp;#8217;s just because I don&amp;#8217;t trust their motivations and have been burned in the past. Being burned in the oil change business isn&amp;#8217;t very expensive, I think the last time I got hooked it was $129 for service I didn&amp;#8217;t really need. I now second guess everything that those people say - often just long enough to say: &lt;em&gt;No thanks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t trust car mechanics because I&amp;#8217;m mechanically illiterate. So that makes me skeptical of their suggestions because of the knowledge gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does that apply to this post?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we&amp;#8217;ve been building websites as &lt;a href='http://nonfiction.ca'&gt;nonfiction studios inc.&lt;/a&gt; for 8 and a half years now. Many of our clients were with us when we started out of the ashes of another studio. We&amp;#8217;ve kept most of them for this entire time and they&amp;#8217;ve developed a trust in us that we&amp;#8217;ve worked hard to keep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we do work with those clients - our long term partners - we are able to do &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better work for them. We don&amp;#8217;t have to fight about simple decisions - they trust we have their best in mind. And we trust that they know their business and that we don&amp;#8217;t - we rely on them for information about their company and clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to get &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of our clients into that position - a position where they will trust us - and allow us to do our best work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a large client that we do a ton of work for - from all sorts of departments. Some of those departments trust us - and we do our best work for them. They have a problem, we discuss the problem and then come up with solutions - they give input from their perspective as business experts - and we give input from a design and development perspective. And in the end, we have a great product - delivered on time and on budget with minimal drama and maximum impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some other departments at that client that don&amp;#8217;t seem to trust our advice at all. We&amp;#8217;re constantly second guessed until the project is a barely recognizable shell of what we designed and planned for. We&amp;#8217;re constantly having to re-do and re-work something that will never deliver - because our advice was consistently ignored - for whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all comes down to trust. We want to earn your trust - so that we can do better work and make you look like a hero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s really our only job - to make you look good - so let&amp;#8217;s work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we do better to earn your trust?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
